<metadata><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Interagency Grizzly Bear Study Team (Bjornlie et al. 2014)</origin><pubdate>2014</pubdate><title>Distribution of the Yellowstone Grizzly Bear (2000-2014)</title><geoform>Vector Digital Data Set (Polygon)</geoform><onlink>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/folder/52fe7f75e4b0354fef6de4f0</onlink><lworkcit><citeinfo><origin>Daniel D. Bjornlie</origin><origin>Daniel J. Thompson</origin><origin>Mark A. Haroldson</origin><origin>Charles C. Schwartz</origin><origin>Kerry A. Gunther</origin><origin>Steven L. Cain</origin><origin>Daniel B. Tyers</origin><origin>Kevin L. Frey</origin><origin>Bryan C. Aber</origin><pubdate>2014</pubdate><title>Methods to estimate distribution and range extent of grizzly bears in the Greater Yellowstone Ecosystem.</title><edition>1</edition><geoform>Publication (Journal)</geoform><serinfo><sername>Wildlife Society Bulletin</sername><issue>38(1):182-187</issue></serinfo><pubinfo><pubplace>Unknown</pubplace><publish>Wildlife Society</publish></pubinfo><onlink>http://www.nrmsc.usgs.gov/science/igbst/detailedpubs</onlink></citeinfo></lworkcit></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>The grizzly bear distribution boundary represents the estimated geographic extent of occupied range of the Yellowstone grizzly bear population for the period 2000-2014.  The distribution boundary was delineated to provide reliable estimations of grizzly bear occupancy throughout time and for use as a monitoring tool in grizzly bear management and conservation. The boundary was delineated by the Interagency Grizzly Bear Study Team (IGBST) using an interpolation method based on grizzly bear telemetry and GPS locations as well as verified observations and signs of grizzly bears inside the Greater Yellowstone ecosystem during 2000 to 2014.</abstract><purpose>The grizzly bear distribution boundary for the Greater Yellowstone Ecosystem was constructed by the Interagency Grizzly Bear Study Team to provide an accurate estimate of occupied range of grizzly bears for the period 2000-2014.  The method for delineating distribution was based on a kriged interpolation technique and was designed to use verified grizzly bear observation and location data from all sources between 2000 and 2014 as well as provide the simplicity to be updated on a frequent basis for management and conservation applications.</purpose><supplinf>For more information on the methods used to generate the distribution boundary, please refer to:  Bjornlie, D. D., D. J. Thompson, M. A. Haroldson, C. C. Schwartz, K. A. Gunther, S. L. Cain, D. B. Tyers, K. L. Frey, and B. Aber.  2014.  Methods to estimate distribution and range extent of grizzly bears in the Greater Yellowstone Ecosystem.  Wildlife Society Bulletin 38:182–187.  ( Available at:  http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/wsb.368/abstract )</supplinf></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><rngdates><begdate>2000</begdate><enddate>2014</enddate></rngdates></timeinfo><current>publication date</current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>As needed</update></status><spdom><descgeog>This distribution boundary encompasses an area surrounding Yellowstone and Grand Teton National Parks and includes portions of Wyoming, Montana, and Idaho.</descgeog><bounding><westbc>-112.244196945</westbc><eastbc>-108.518802928</eastbc><northbc>45.700683122</northbc><southbc>42.478713022</southbc></bounding></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>None</themekt><themekey>Grizzly Bear</themekey><themekey>distribution</themekey><themekey>boundary</themekey><themekey>Occupancy</themekey></theme><place><placekt>None</placekt><placekey>Yellowstone</placekey><placekey>Montana</placekey><placekey>Wyoming</placekey><placekey>Idaho</placekey><placekey>Grand Teton</placekey><placekey>Beaverhead-Deerlodge</placekey><placekey>Bridger-Teton</placekey><placekey>Caribou-Targhee</placekey><placekey>Gallatin-Custer</placekey><placekey>Shoshone</placekey></place></keywords><accconst>These data are preliminary or provisional and are subject to revision. They are being provided to meet the need for timely best science. The data have not received final approval by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) and are provided on the condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government shall be held liable for any damages resulting from the authorized or unauthorized use of the data.</accconst><useconst>No use constraints are associated with this data.</useconst><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, NORTHWEST REGION</cntorg><cntper>Frank T van Manen</cntper></cntorgp><cntpos>Supervisory Research Wildlife Biologist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing address</addrtype><address>2327 University Way</address><city>Bozeman</city><state>MT</state><postal>59715</postal><country>United States</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>406-994-5043</cntvoice><cntfax>406-994-6416</cntfax><cntemail>fvanmanen@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac><datacred>U.S. Geological Survey, Wyoming Game and Fish Department, National Park Service, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, Montana Fish, Wildlife and Parks, U.S. Forest Service, Idaho Department of Fish and Game, Eastern Shoshone and Northern Arapaho Tribal Fish and Game Department.</datacred><native>Environment as of Metadata Creation: Microsoft [Unknown] Version 6.2 (Build 9200) ; Esri ArcGIS 10.4.1 (Build 5696) Service Pack N/A (Build N/A)</native></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted.</attraccr></attracc><logic>No formal logical accuracy tests were conducted.</logic><complete>Data set is considered complete for the information presented, as described in the abstract. Users are advised to read the rest of the metadata record carefully for additional details.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>No formal positional accuracy tests were conducted.</horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>A formal accuracy assessment of the vertical positional information in the data set has either not been conducted, or is not applicable.</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><lineage><procstep><procdesc>We used a geographic information system software package (ArcGIS v. 10.0, ESRI) to construct the grizzly bear distribution boundary for the time period 2000-2014. Boundary delineation was accomplished by overlaying all verified grizzly bear locations from all sources between 2000-2014 on a 3-km x 3-km grid and using zonal analysis and ordinary kriging to develop a predicted surface of occupied grizzly bear range. The following steps outline the process used.</procdesc><procdate>2015</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>1. A shapefile of verified grizzly bear location data for the period 2000–2014 was compiled by the Interagency Grizzly Bear Study Team and consisted of GPS and very high frequency telemetry locations; locations of observations or tracks reported or verified by experienced agency personnel; locations associated with grizzly bear-human conflicts, mortalities, and scats or hair samples attributed to grizzly bears via DNA analysis.</procdesc><procdate>2015</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>2. We used the Create Fishnet tool in the Data Management/Sampling toolbox to construct a polygon fishnet (grid) comprised of 3-km x 3-km squares for an area containing all verified grizzly bear locations in the Greater Yellowstone Ecosystem (GYE). The grid-cell size of 3-km was based on the mean daily activity radius of 1.5 km for male grizzly bears in the GYE.</procdesc><procdate>2015</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>3. We then overlaid the 2000-2014 location point data on the fishnet grid and used the Select by Location functionality to identify cells containing 1 or more location data points. Cells with at least one location point were assigned a value of 1 and unoccupied cells a value of 0 to denote grizzly bear presence/absence.</procdesc><procdate>2015</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>4. The attributed polygon fishnet was converted to a raster using the Feature to Raster tool in the Conversion/To Raster toolbox. The presence/absence attribute of 1 or 0 were maintained for each 3-km x 3-km raster cell.</procdesc><procdate>2015</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>5. To account for unoccupied cells resulting from missing data within known grizzly bear distribution, we performed zonal analysis by applying the Focal Statistics tool in the Spatial Analyst toolbox to sum, for each input cell, the value of the target cell and all 8 adjacent cells. The resulting zonal raster thus had potential cell values ranging from 0 to 9.</procdesc><procdate>2015</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>6. We then applied the Raster to Point tool in the Conversion/From Raster toolbox on the zonal raster to generate a center-point feature for each 3-km x 3-km cell with the zonal sum attribute maintained for each center-point.</procdesc><procdate>2015</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>7. We then used the Kriging Method in the Geostatistical Wizard (accessed from the Geostatistical Analyst toolbar) in ArcGIS to interpolate a predicted distribution surface from known points of grizzly bear presence. In the Kriging/CoKriging dialog box, the centroid point file was specified as the Source Dataset and the attribute field containing centroid values of 0-9 was entered as the Data Field. In the Kriging step 2 dialog box, we selected “Ordinary” for Kriging Type; “Prediction” for Output Surface Type; and “None” for Transformation type and Order of trend removal. The resulting kriged layer was reclassified to integer values and exported as a “Filled Contour” vector of “Draft” contour quality to avoid over-smoothing. Contours were then dissolved into a single polygon feature to represent the grizzly bear distribution boundary feature.</procdesc><procdate>2015</procdate></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spdoinfo><direct>Vector</direct><ptvctinf><sdtsterm><sdtstype>G-polygon</sdtstype><ptvctcnt>1</ptvctcnt></sdtsterm></ptvctinf></spdoinfo><spref><horizsys><planar><gridsys><gridsysn>Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone>12</utmzone><transmer><sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer><longcm>-111.0</longcm><latprjo>0.0</latprjo><feast>500000.0</feast><fnorth>0.0</fnorth></transmer></utm></gridsys><planci><plance>coordinate pair</plance><coordrep><absres>0.6096</absres><ordres>0.6096</ordres></coordrep><plandu>Meter</plandu></planci></planar><geodetic><horizdn>D_North_American_1983</horizdn><ellips>GRS_1980</ellips><semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis><denflat>298.257222101</denflat></geodetic></horizsys></spref><eainfo><detailed><enttyp><enttypl>Attribute Table</enttypl><enttypd>Table containing attribute information associated with the data set.</enttypd><enttypds>Producer defined</enttypds></enttyp><attr><attrlabl>Id</attrlabl><attrdef>Unique polygon identifier</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>0</rdommin><rdommax>0</rdommax></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Boundary</attrlabl><attrdef>Descriptive title of boundary feature.</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Grizzly bear distribution in the GYE, 2000-2014</edomv><edomvd>Descriptive title of boundary feature.</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>Acres</attrlabl><attrdef>Area of boundary feature measured in acres</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>14409702.6527</rdommin><rdommax>14409702.6527</rdommax></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>SqKm</attrlabl><attrdef>Area of boundary feature measured in square kilometers</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>58313.9977251</rdommin><rdommax>58313.9977251</rdommax></rdom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>File_Link</attrlabl><attrdef>Internal USGS web link</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><edom><edomv>https://prd-wret.s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/assets/palladium/production/s3fs-public/atoms/files/Occupied_Range_2000-2014.pdf</edomv><edomvd>Unknown</edomvd><edomvds>Producer defined</edomvds></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl>SQ_MI</attrlabl><attrdef>Area of boundary feature measured in square miles</attrdef><attrdefs>Producer defined</attrdefs><attrdomv><rdom><rdommin>22515.1603978</rdommin><rdommax>22515.1603978</rdommax></rdom></attrdomv></attr></detailed><overview><eaover>The entity and attribute information provided here describes the tabular data associated with the data set. Please review the detailed descriptions that are provided (the individual attribute descriptions) for information on the values that appear as fields/table entries of the data set.</eaover><eadetcit>The entity and attribute information was generated by the individual and/or agency identified as the originator of the data set. Please review the rest of the metadata record for additional details and information.</eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><distrib><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>Frank T van Manen</cntper><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, NORTHWEST REGION</cntorg></cntperp><cntpos>Supervisory Research Wildlife Biologist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing address</addrtype><address>2327 University Way</address><city>Bozeman</city><state>MT</state><postal>59715</postal><country>United States</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>406-994-5043</cntvoice><cntfax>406-994-6416</cntfax><cntemail>fvanmanen@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></distrib><distliab>These data are preliminary or provisional and are subject to revision. They are being provided to meet the need for timely best science. The data have not received final approval by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) and are provided on the condition that neither the USGS nor the U.S. Government shall be held liable for any damages resulting from the authorized or unauthorized use of the data.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>Vector Digital Data Set (Polygon)</formname></digtinfo><digtopt><onlinopt><computer><networka><networkr>https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/folder/52fe7f75e4b0354fef6de4f0</networkr></networka></computer></onlinopt></digtopt></digform><fees>None. No fees are applicable for obtaining the data set.</fees></stdorder></distinfo><metainfo><metd>20170508</metd><metc><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>Lisa Landenburger</cntper><cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey, NORTHWEST REGION</cntorg></cntperp><cntpos>Physical Scientist</cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing address</addrtype><address>2327 University Way</address><city>Bozeman</city><state>MT</state><postal>59715</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>406-994-7430</cntvoice><cntfax>406-994-6556</cntfax><cntemail>lisa_landenburger@usgs.gov</cntemail></cntinfo></metc><metstdn>FDGC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata and
Biological Data Profile</metstdn><metstdv>FDGC-STD-001-1998</metstdv></metainfo></metadata>